

# MD. FERDOUS WAHID

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR

DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRICAL AND ELECTRONIC ENGINEERING HAJEE MOHAMMAD DANESH SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY UNIVERSITY

+8801718844106

② Dinajpur-5200, Bangladesh

mfwahid26@gmail.com

☐ https://hstu.ac.bd/teacher/ferdous

IEB Membership No. M41193

IEEE Membership No. 94608483

# **EDUCATION**

# MSc (Engg.) in ECE

Khulna University of Engineering and Technology Ongoing

# BSc (Engg.) in ECE

Khulna University of Engineering and Technology 2008 - 2012

## **EXPERTISE**

- **Programming:** C, Python, Pandas, Numpy, Matplotlib, Tensorflow, Keras, OpenCV, Seaborn, MATLAB.
- Application Sofware: Origin, MultiSim, Proteus, CASTEP, MS Office, LATEX.

# SCHOLARSHIP RECEIVED

- Technical scholarship (2008-2012), Khulna University of Engineering and Technology (KUET), Khulna.
- Secondary School Certificate Scholarship (2005).

# **PROFILE**

I have over 10 years of teaching experience in the field of engineering, particularly in Electrical and Electronic Engineering. My expertise encompasses the development of internet-of-things based intelligent systems and computer aided medical diagnosis system development using machine learning. I also have distinguished record of publication in academic journals and conferences all over the world. Skilled in working with various machine learning tools and python language.

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### **ASSISTANT PROFESSOR**

September 2018 - Present

Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering Hajee Mohammad Danesh Science and Technology University Dinajpur-5200, Bangladesh.

#### **LECTURER**

September 2015 - September 2018

Department of Electrical and Electronic Engineering Hajee Mohammad Danesh Science and Technology University Dinajpur-5200, Bangladesh.

#### **LECTURER**

May 2013 - September 2015

Department of Electronics and Communication Engineering Sylhet International University Sylhet-3100, Bangladesh.

# **RESEARCH PROJECTS**

- 1. DETECTION OF DIABETIC RETINOPATHY FROM RETINAL FUNDUS IMAGES USING MULTILAYERED CONVOLUTIONAL NEURAL NETWORK Funded by: Institute of Research and Training (IRT), HSTU | FY: 2021-2022 Position: Principle Investigator (PI)
- 2. HSTU BAYANNODB: A BENCHMARK DATABASE OF ISOLATED BANGLA HANDWRITTEN BASIC CHARACTERS AND NUMERALS Funded by: Institute of Research and Training (IRT), HSTU | FY: 2020-2021 Position: Principle Investigator (PI)

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- Journal Papers (11)
- Conference Papers (26)

# PROFESSIONAL PLATFORM

Researchgate Account:
 https://www.researchgate.net
 /profile/Md-Wahid-7

• ORCID ID: https://orcid.org/0009-0003-4840-9948

## **LANGUAGE**

- · English Fluent
- Bangla Native

**3.** TWO HANDED BANGLA SIGN LANGUAGE RECOGNITION USING DEEP CONVOLUTIONAL NEURAL NETWORK AND SUPPORT VECTOR MACHINE

**Funded by:** Institute of Research and Training (IRT), HSTU | FY: 2019-2020 **Position:** Principle Investigator (PI)

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### Journal Papers (Q1)

- **1.** M.S. Rahman, A. K. Datta, S. Islam, M. M. Hasan, U. Das, M. A. Sayed, **M.F. Wahid**, A. Ghosh, D. D. Ria, "Insights from computational analysis on novel Lead-Free FrGeCl3 perovskite solar cell using DFT and SCAPS-1D," Inorganic Chemistry Communications, 2024, 113578, ISSN 1387-7003, doi:10.1016/j.inoche.2024.113578.
- 2. M. F. Wahid, M. S. Rahman, N. Ahmed, A. A. Mamun, M. N. Howlader, T. Paul, M. M. R. Tareq, M. S. Rahman and M. M. Rahman "Performance Enhancement of Lead-Free CsSnI3 Perovskite Solar Cell: Design and Simulation With Different Electron Transport Layers," in IEEE Access, vol. 12, pp. 8296-8312, 2024, doi: 10.1109/ACCESS.2024.3352444.
- **3.** N. Sultan, M. Hasan, **M. F. Wahid**, H. Saha and A. Habib, "Cesarean Section Classification Using Machine Learning With Feature Selection, Data Balancing, and Explainability," in IEEE Access, vol. 11, pp. 84487-84499, 2023, doi: 10.1109/ACCESS.2023.3303342.

#### **Conference Papers (2024)**

- **1.** M. S. Rahman, A. K. Datta and **M. F. Wahid**, "A Theoretical Study on Non-Leaded Sr3NCl3 Perovskite through SCAPS-1D Using DFT-Derived Properties," 2024 15th International Conference on Computing Communication and Networking Technologies (ICCCNT), Kamand, India, 2024, pp. 1-6, doi: 10.1109/ICCCNT61001.2024.10725338.
- **2.** M. R. Hoshen, A. Mimi Choity and **M. F. Wahid**, "Design of Transformer Theft Prevention System Utilizing an Integrated Sensor Network and Real-Time Alerting," 2024 8th International Conference on I-SMAC (IoT in Social, Mobile, Analytics and Cloud) (I-SMAC), Kirtipur, Nepal, 2024, pp. 560-565, doi: 10.1109/I-SMAC61858.2024.10714787.
- **3.** M. S. Rahman, U. Das, M. A. K. Mia and **M. F. Wahid**, "Computational Evaluation of Lead Free MoSe2-Based Thin Film Solar Cell for Enhanced Photovoltaic Performance," 2024 International Conference on Advances in Computing, Communication, Electrical, and Smart Systems (iCACCESS), Dhaka, Bangladesh, 2024, pp. 1-6, doi: 10.1109/iCACCESS61735.2024.10499537.
- **4.** U. Das, M. S. Rahman, S. Paul, B. K. Paul and **M. F. Wahid**, "Numerical Investigation of Lead-Free CH3NH3SnI3 Perovskite Solar Cell for Photovoltaic Performance Improvement using SCAPS-1D," 2024 International Conference on Advances in Computing, Communication, Electrical, and Smart Systems (iCACCESS), Dhaka, Bangladesh, 2024, pp. 01-06, doi: 10.1109/iCACCESS61735.2024.10499601.